OpenAI is losing more than two
dollars for every dollar it makes.
Their Q1 2026 operating margin was -122%.
They are on pace to undershoot its
ad revenue projections by 90 percent.
ChatGPT's market share has dropped
below 50% for the first time ever.
Their enterprise share has
been cut nearly in half.
And Sam Altman just admitted it himself:
OpenAI has "not had our best 12 months ever,
and it's mostly my fault."
How did this happen?
ChatGPT has over 900 million weekly users.
It’s the company that started the AI race,
which is now falling behind.
Can they still catch up?
To answer these questions, we need to look at
the state of OpenAI, now, and how we got here.
The first tipping point wasn’t
actually Anthropic… but Gemini.
In November 2025, Gemini 3 beat GPT-5.1
across essentially every benchmark.
This caused Altman to issue
a “code red” at OpenAI.
Though, OpenAI still had a gigantic lead.
Over 1.1 billion users, with Gemini at 662
million, and Claude with 245 million.
But, these numbers are quite deceptive.
OpenAI has a lot of users… but their control
on the markets that matter, is shrinking.
In May, ChatGPT’s global assistant share
dropped below 50% for the first time,
to 46%, with Gemini at 28% and Claude at 10%.
It seems like OpenAI is still in the lead, but,
things get a lot worse for OpenAI, when we look
at what actually makes money: enterprise spending.
And oh boy, is it bad.
“We estimate Anthropic now
earns 40% of enterprise LLM spend, up from 24%
last year and 12% in 2023. Over the same period,
OpenAI lost nearly half of its enterprise
share, falling to 27% from 50% in 2023.
Google also saw significant gains, increasing its
enterprise share from 7% in 2023 to 21% in 2025.”
This is one of the biggest foundational problems,
and a big part of this is coding, where LLMs have
seen some of the most successful return.
Anthropic now has 54% of the coding market,
with OpenAI at just 21%.
And part of the challenge
is the delay or restraint of computing power.
About 40% of US data centres planned for 2026
are already delayed, transformer lead times
have stretched to five years in some regions,
and OpenAI has cancelled sites in
the UK, Norway and Lordstown, Ohio.
OpenAI is struggling in the deep,
high revenue niches that matter.
But, there’s another part
we need to talk about. Ads.
OpenAI, and others, have claimed that ads are
their saving grace. And it very well could be.
The way to monetise the free tier.
Because, boy are there a lot of them.
Out of 900-910 million weekly active
users, 95% of them are on the free service.
Hence why OpenAI set a target of
$100 billion in ad revenue for 2030.
If they can’t dominate coding or enterprise,
maybe they can be the mass market ad service?
Well…
OpenAI’s ad
business is on pace to miss this by 90%.
In fact, the standalone AI chatbots,
like ChatGPT, Gemini, Copilot, Google AI Mode,
and more, will have cumulatively generated
under $1 billion in 2026 in ad revenue.
By 2030? It’s expected to be just $5.41
billion, across the entire market.
“OpenAI's single-company 2030 target
is roughly 20 times larger than eMarketer's
estimate for the entire U.S. chatbot ad market.”
But, why?
They have so many users,
why can’t they monetise them?
A few reasons.
It turns out, prompt replies are
surprisingly hard to advertise on.
Only about 2% of ChatGPT prompts, aka what
the person is searching, involve purchasable
products. So it’s hard to sell something,
when the prompt doesn’t relate in any way.
Hence, ChatGPT ads have a terrible
click through rate of 0.91-1.3%.
For context, Google search ads are around
29.2%. Where basically everything you search,
has some kind of relevant ad.
AI might be taking a lot of web
traffic from search results… but it sure
doesn’t seem to be taking the ad revenue.
According to advertisers, the ad
tech stack is also still “primitive”.
“CPMs on the ad business have already
collapsed from $60 to as low as $25”
To make matters worse, 80% of users sent fewer
than 1,000 messages all year, in 2025. An average
of fewer than 3 prompts per day. So the chance
to see ads, let alone relevant ads, isn’t great.
But with all that said, none of that
matters if OpenAI is actually making money.
So, how is that looking?
Well, OpenAI have two,
gigantic problems to deal
with before they can start.
Let’s look at things right now:
OpenAI has forecasted a $14 billion
loss for all of 2026, with losses totalling
$44 billion from 2023 through to 2029.
But then, we got the Q1 2026 results, with a $6.95
billion operating loss on $5.7 billion in revenue,
which is a -122% operating margin.
So, for every dollar OpenAI made,
they spent more than two.
They are one quarter into the
financial year and have already used half
of the loss they projected for all of it.
Once you add stock compensation, $2.3 billion, the
GAAP operating loss is as high as $9.3 billion.
FutureSearch now forecasts a
$33 billion GAAP loss for 2026.
But as we’ll soon find out, these
losses aren’t nearly the entire picture.
OpenAI needs to start making some real
money, which is proving difficult.
OpenAI promised revenue would
start booming… eventually.
And revenue was… and technically
still is growing, but…
Not so much anymore.
[Dan Schwarz, FutureSearch]:“OpenAI grew
from $6 billion to roughly $25 billion ARR
over the 17 months to May 2026. Growth then
flattened: the run rate held near $25 billion
from February through the spring. OpenAI's
internal target for mid-2027 is $62 billion.
My forecast median is $44 billion.”
ChatGPT weekly active users have
also plateaued at around 900 million, with
only 50 million being paying subscribers.
OpenAI can’t seem to monetise
their exorbitant user-base.
Which, is important, because of OpenAI’s
massive bills and capital commitments.
Starting in 2027, OpenAI will be paying
Oracle $300 billion across 5 years,
for cloud capacity, about 4.5 GW, or the
electricity of about four million homes.
They have a deal with AWS for $38 billion across
seven years, for access to mass amounts of Nvidia
GB200 and GB300 GPUs. Then it expanded that
agreement by $100 billion across eight years.
OpenAI has also committed to $250 billion
in Microsoft Azure, aka cloud services,
as well as 10 GW of custom AI accelerators from
Broadcom. Basically, OpenAI will design its own
chip, with Broadcom building it. We don’t know
exactly how much this will be, but the Financial
Times estimated between $350 and $500 billion.
There are even more agreements, but in total,
according to CFO Sarah Friar, OpenAI has current
commitments of $750 billion through 2030. And
remember, there’s way more spend beyond 2030…
Though, we also need extra context.
These are massive bills, but most of these
companies are also funneling money into OpenAI.
They just announced a $110 billion funding round,
twice the size of their last raise. “Amazon
invested $50 billion, Nvidia invested $30 billion
and SoftBank invested $30 billion in the round”.
Worldwide AI spending is estimated to reach
$2.59 trillion in 2026, a 47% increase over 2025.
The Magnificent Seven have planned more
than $700 billion in AI capex for 2026,
up from roughly $400 billion in 2025.
This gives us insight into OpenAI’s runway.
Their cash reserves and marketable securities
are at $73 billion. So they do have cash on hand,
and that’s up from $40 billion at the end of 2025.
But, they’ve promised a lot of money,
to quite a few companies.
And they’re burning through cash very quickly.
So, can OpenAI catch up?
One thing people point to for this,
is their IPO. This has potential
for a gigantic capital injection.
Sam Altman believes OpenAI has a
valuation well over $1 trillion.
But, now they’ve pushed it back, to next year.
And, it makes sense as to why.
OpenAI isn’t winning the race anymore.
Well, they are in pure user counts,
but not much else.
Which brings us to the big problem.
OpenAI signed contractual obligations
against revenue that hadn’t arrived yet.
But OpenAI was winning. So they committed big.
Though now, they’re no longer winning the AI race,
but still spent the winnings of said race…
Here’s where things get really interesting though.
At the BlackRock Infrastructure Summit in March
2026, Sam Altman said something important.
Something massive is happening in AI,
not too dissimilar to other industries.
It turns out, Altman might be right,
but, maybe not in the way he hopes.
This is bad for all AI model
companies, not just OpenAI.
If you’ve watched this far, consider
subscribing! You probably enjoy our
stuff, and it helps the channel too! Thanks.
Let’s give that earlier quote, a bit more context.
Altman is referencing a phrase made
by Lewis Strauss, Chair of the Atomic
Energy Commission in the 50s, where he said
[Lewis Strauss]: “It is not too much to expect
that our children will enjoy in their homes
electrical energy too cheap to meter — will
know of great periodic regional famines
in the world only as matters of history,—
will travel effort­lessly over the seas and
under them and through the air with a minimum
of danger and at great speeds, — and will
experience a lifespan far longer than ours”
This was his prediction about nuclear power,
which never came true. Something else happened.
Electricity became one of the most tightly
regulated industries in the developed world.
It still became a commodity,
with extremely thin margins.
A part of that ecosystem
absolutely makes a ton of money.
The turbine makers, transformer manufacturers,
and transmission networks are very profitable.
The value in electricity, moved down the
stack, or rather, it was always there anyway.
What makes all of this, so ironic, is that
Sam Altman literally predicted all of this.
In his June 2025 essay The Gentle Singularity,
he wrote that “as datacentre
production gets automated,
the cost of intelligence should eventually
converge to near the cost of electricity.”
It’s not just electricity either.
This clip must make it into the edit).
The internet eventually turned into a commodity.
A gigabit from Brand A is the same as Brand B,
so a customer has no reason to
consider anything but price.
The part that makes real money,
accumulates where it can’t move.
For a while, the companies selling the
actual equipment, like Cisco, and Corning.
Cisco was briefly the most valuable
company in the world in 2000.
But when the buildout of internet infrastructure
largely stopped, the value collapsed.
Now, the value is up the stack in the consumer
end. Companies like Google or Netflix,
who have all your data, information, habits, have
a high switching cost, just not a monetary one.
So how does this relate to AI?
Because the exact same thing is happening.
In 2023, both GPUs and AI models were scarce.
But now, in 2026,
GPUs are still scarce, models are not.
And they’re all getting closer and closer.
“The gap between the best closed model and the
best open-weight model on Chatbot Arena fell from
8.04% in January 2024 to 1.70% in February 2025.
The supply side is now effectively infinite. The
scarce asset becomes the ability to run them well
— throughput, latency, cost per token, routing,
caching, fine-tuning, evaluation, and guardrails.”
The value in all of these areas, accumulates
where it is hardest to substitute.
The value, accumulating down the stack.
At the bottom, with the most “mass”, or
value, are the semiconductors and compute.
“NVIDIA’s data-center revenue hit $75.2B, up
92% year over year, at a ~75% gross margin:
roughly a $300B annualized run-rate”
The money is in companies selling GPUs,
semiconductors, compute. Not intelligence.
That might change, if the supply for GPUs
and compute outweighs demand.
There is also value near the top
layer, not in ChatGPT, but in
third-party, consumer-facing software.
But this is rather thin, as AI apps have
lower margins than regular SaaS products.
Just look at Amazon.
They’re cutting back their AI model, Nova,
because, at least I believe, they’ve figured out
this part of the industry isn't the money maker.
It’s the one below it.
This is why OpenAI is in such a tough spot.
They are stuck in the least valuable layer.
And as there are more comparable models,
and prices come down, paying those
massive bills might be tough.
What’s interesting is how AI and intelligence
have become a commodity, which is in tokens.
Charged by use, like electricity.
And now, token cost has even gone “far
beyond the costs of the employees”.
But, something weird has happened.
Tokens aren’t actually getting more expensive.
The price of a single token has
fallen by about 90% since 2023.
So, if intelligence and tokens are
cheaper, why is AI spend getting so much bigger?
Click here to learn the other side of the story.